Do
you, Table 1, agree to union
with Table 2, combining
your first name, last
name, and city columns?
And I mean vertically,
not horizontally, because
horizontally would be a join,
and this is a union ceremony.
And do you, Table 2,
agree to union with Table 1,
stacking your rows together into
one beautiful result set? And
again, vertically, not horizontally,
because that would require
counseling from an inner join.
if anyone objects to this union
please raise a syntax air now or
forever hold your semicolon i now
pronounce you union you may select
the bride exclaimers this ceremony
supports compatible data types
only these tables have agreed
to remove duplicates from their
relationship union always considered
but there were too many duplicates
in the family for legal reasons
no values are considered equal and
hopefully sticks with you that's
pretty much everything i want to
mention about the union operator we
we're adding this short section to
5300 because we do get some feedback
from students that they are asked
about it in interviews and typically
the question is what is the
difference between a union and a join
here's the formula for union based
on set theory so if you had table
a union table b what's what that's
equivalent to is you're adding
table a some columns and then you're
adding rows table b below that and
then this subtraction of a intersect
b simply means if there's any duplicate
information you would subtract
that out So union, we can add
vertically and then remove duplicates.
And here we have an example of a join.
As you can see, joins typically
expand horizontally where
we add columns from one
table, for instance, Halloween
events, and columns from
another, the monster sighting.
Here's some code for the set operator
union, and then I'll get to some
rules. but we have select location
from Halloween events and then the
word union and then below that would
be the second table select location
from monster sightings and you can
see the result on the on the right
hand of the screen. As a reminder
the union gets rid of any duplicates
so if there are duplicate locations
they will be removed. In addition
if you want to create an alias
for this particular code you would
include the alias in the initial select
statement and if you wanted to do
an order by, you would do the order
by in the last select statement.
And we also have another option if
you do want to include duplicate
information is the union all.
So in this code we have a union
with no duplicates and we have a
union all where we have duplicates.
You can see old man Jaken's
mansion is listed twice and so
the difference between those union
all includes duplicates. If the
two were run and you tested to
see which had better performance,
which run more quickly. Obviously
union all would run faster
because it doesn't have to go find
duplicates and remove those. In
addition to that the data type
should be the same so character
data lines up with character data
and ideally the meaning as well.
If you're adding and stacking
it only makes sense if the
meaning between those columns
between those tables are the same.
And then the other two
duplicates are removed for union
and finally null values are
considered equal and as you
know nulls always have kind
of an exception to the rule.
And this will be the last slide
I'll show you here. As you can see,
this appears to be a union all.
And the reason for that is you can
see that Kim Mills null and Kim
Mills null. So this is repeated. If
we ran a union on this, the question
is, are these considered equal?
If they're considered equal, then
it would only show up one time. If
they're not, the nulls are not
considered equal, it would show up
twice. If this were just the union
because Kim is the same as Kim and
Mills is the same as Mills. Nulls
are considered equal and so if you
just ran the union, it would remove
one of these pieces of information.
That's a brief overview of the
union. We'll go into more detail
in 5310 if you take that class,
but that should be enough to get
you through any interview question
asking about the union. Take care.
Disclaimers. This ceremony supports
compatible data types only.
These tables have agreed to remove
duplicates from their relationship.
Union all was considered, but
there were too many duplicates
in the family. For legal reasons,
no values are considered equal.